Chauncey Wright Papers 1850-1875 Mss.B.W933
American Philosophical Society
Chauncey Wright Papers
1850-1875
Mss.B.W933
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
A philosopher, metaphysician, and mathematician, Chauncey Wright graduated from Harvard in 1852 and taught occasionally at the College while employed as a "computer" with the American Ephemeris and Nautical Almanac. A positivist and empiricist in the British tradition, he exerted an influence on the development of American Pragmatism through his younger friends William James, Charles S. Peirce, and Oliver Wendell Holmes, but is perhaps best remembered as one of the earliest and most able defenders of Darwinism and Darwinian natural selection. The bulk of the 137 items in the Wright Papers is comprised of personal letters addressed to Wright during the adult years of his brief life. From the typical letters of a college student, the correspondence branches out to touch upon philosophy, mathematics, and Wright's meeting with Darwin in 1872. Among the more prominent correspondents are C. S. Peirce, Charles Eliot Norton, Francis Bowen, Susan and J. Peter Lesley, and James Bradley Thayer and William Sydney Thayer.
Wright, Chauncey,1830-1875.
Bibliography
Wright, Chauncey, Letters of Chauncey Wright, ed. by James Bradley Thayer (Cambridge, Mass.: J. Wilson and Son, 1878) Call no.: B W933t
Wright, Chauncey, Philosophical Discussions (N.Y.: Holt, 1877) Call no.: 104 W93
Related Archival Materials note
The Harvard University Archives also contain a small collection of the Papers of Chauncey Wright. He appears as a correspondent as well in the Records of the North American Review at the Houghton Library, Harvard.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Acquired from Chauncey Wright Pearson, August 1978 (1978-1252ms).
Scope and Contents note
Frustratingly sparse, the surviving papers of Chauncey Wright nevertheless provide glimpses into the mind and personality of one of America's great philosophers of the mid-nineteenth century. Primarily personal in nature, and nearly all addresssed to Wright, these letters span most of Wright's brief life from his last two years as a student at Harvard bewteen 1850-1852 until nearly the end of his life in 1875.
In a small handful of letters, Wright's philosophical and intellectual interests shine through. There is a particularly fine exchange of letters with Francis Bowen regarding Wright's theory of the mathematics and metaphysics of the honeycomb, but these also relate more generally to Wright's perspective on causality. As might be expected, Mill's philosophy comes up repeatedly, especially in letters from Bowen, Edwin Lawrence Godkin, Catherine Innes Ireland, and Charles Sanders Peirce, and Mills' and Wright's thoughts of the equality of sexes appears in several of these letters, and in a letter from Sara Sedgwick. Of particular interest in this regard is a letter from C. S. Peirce to Wright, September 2, 1865, working through the mathematics of a card trick, but also through Mill's discussion of free will and his criticism of William Hamilton. Peirce believed Mill's arguments were ingenious, but aimed with "malicious intent. Mill wants to root out this philosophy, by adequate arguments or by inadequate ones."
Darwin appears as a subject in letters from Charles Eliot Norton, who was delighted that Wright had visited Darwin in 1872. Having learned that Wright had dined at Down House, Norton effused about Darwin: "He is a man whose personal qualities, only to be known by acquaintance with him in his own home, complete and satisfy the highest conception of him that one may have formed from his books. He is one of the most satisfactory of men." A receipt from the Massachusetts Historical Society acknowledges the gift of Wright's famous essay against St. George Mivart's Genesis of Species.
Other letters in the collection provide brief glimpses into the personal and political context of Wright's intellectual circle. The letters from Reginald Heber Chase, a Harvard classmate, provide some particularly pointed references to the politics of the Civil War and digust over the draft, the president, and the state of the nation. Still less happily, Wright became entangled in the controversy over the Dudley Observatory and earned the umbrage of Benjamin Apthorp Gould. The sole letter from Wright in this collection is a draft reply to Gould. There are two school essays by Wright in the collection, and a poem, the "Posivitivist Hymn."
The 137 items in the Wright Papers are arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
Biographical/Historical note
A philosopher, metaphysician, mathematician, and Darwinian stalwart, Chauncey Wright was born in Northampton, Mass., on September 20, 1830. The son of Ansel Wright, a grocer and constable, and Elizabeth Boleyn, Wright was an able student with a particular aptitude for the quantitative sciences, and his reputation for scholarship earned him the largesse of a local philanthropist that enabled him to attend Harvard as an undergraduate. After his graduation in 1852, he benefited further from the influence of friends, most notably William James, who helped secure him a lectureship at the College. A standard academic position, however, was not immeidately in the cards, however. For all his intellectual talents, his affability and sociability, he proved to be a miserable teacher, dull and often incomprehensible from a student's pespective, and as a result, he failed to flourish in the academy.
In 1852, Wright therefore took an appointment as a "computer" with the American Ephemeris and Nautical Almanac, a position that provided him with sufficient financial support and, more importantly, sufficient time to devote himself to intellectual cultivation and collegiality. His home in Cambridge became a modern day salon beginning in the later 1850s, attracting colleagues from Harvard and the Almanac. By 1872, this lifelong bachelor had become one of the elders of the proto-pragmatist Metaphysical Club, a veritable "boxing-master" for his junior colleagues C. S. Peirce, William James, and the younger Oliver Wendell Holmes, renowned for his prowess in intellectual jousts. Although they never eventuated into an ongoing appointment, his connections to Harvard circles earned him a one year lectureship in psychology in 1870-1871,and he subsequently taught mathematical physics there to an small, but indifferent crowd of students.
Publishing principally, though too seldom, in the North American Review and The Nation, Wright established himself during the 1860s as an important American philosopher. He was best known, perhaps, as one of the early and most adept proponents of Darwinian thought in America, and he was an ardent defender of natural selection against the plethora of alternative evolutionary mechanisms. His support for Darwin and his attack on Saint George Mivart in the North American Review, brought Wright to Darwin's personal attention and earned him the naturalist's regard and sincere appreciation. During a visit to England in 1872, his only trip abroad, Wright garnered a special invitation to visit Darwin at Down House, an incident he later recalled as one of the highlights of his life.
As a philosopher, Wright grew away from an early allegiance to the Common Sense writings of Thomas Reid and his student William Hamilton to take up a radical version of the new British empiricism. The catalyst to this transformation was Wright's reading of John Stuart Mill, and particularly Mill's devastating critique of Hamilton, although Wright subsequently modified Mill. In turn, Wright's radical empiricism influenced the rising generation of pragmatist philosophers, most notably his Metaphysical colleagues Holmes, James, and Peirce. Insisting on the primacy of empirically-deteremined "facts" over a priori elements, Wright sketched a theory of knowledge based larged opn empiricist contingency rather than a priori certainty. His insistence that science remain free of metaphysical or theological assumptions has remained influential in scientific epistemology led him to reject the writings of Herbert Spencer, whose allegiance to empiricism and evolutionism might otherwise appear palatable. Spencer's insistence upon "law" and invariability and his inveterate teleology, however, led Wright to dismiss his writings as mere metaphysical speculation. Wright was also became known for his efforts to apply natural selective theory to human psychological development, prefiguring modern evolutionary epistemology.
Never a hale figure, Wright's health declined in the late 1860s and 1870s. He suffered from a bout of whooping cough in 1869 and years of too little sleep and too much drinking and smoking took their toll. Late at night on September 11, 1875, Wright suffered a stroke while sitting at his desk, and while he was discovered alive on the following morning, a second led to his death.
Agassiz, Elizabeth Cabot Cary, 1822-1907; Bowen, Francis, 1811-1890; Chase, Reginald Heber, 1832-1885; Comfort, George Fisk, 1833-1910; Darwin, Charles, 1809-1882; Dudley Observatoy; Godkin, William Lawrence, 1831-1902; Gould, Benjamin Apthorp, 1824-1896; Hamilton, William, 1788-1856; Harvard College; Ireland, Catherine Innes; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903; Lesley, Susan I., (Susan Inches), 1823-1904; Mill, John Stuart, 1806-1873; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908; Oliver, James Edward, 1829-1895; Peirce, Charles S., (Charles Sanders), 1839-1914; Pratt, Orson, 1811-1881; Sedgwick, Sara; Thayer, James Bradley, 1831-1902; Thayer, William Sydney, 1864-1932; American Ephemeris and Nautical Almanac; Bees.; Card tricks; Epistemology; Materialism; Mathematics; Metaphysics; Mormons; Philosophy; Probability; Statistics; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865
- Chauncey Wright Papers, 1850-1875; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, n.d.; 3 ALsS; Agassiz, Elizabeth Cabot Cary, 1822-1907
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1875 July 26; ALS; Andrew, John F.
    Scope and Contents note
    Has seen the Psycho and finds Wright's theory of it convincing.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1850 June 5; ALS; Boies, William
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1860-1864; 4 ALsS; Bowen, Francis, 1811-1890
    Mathematics and bees' construction of the honeycomb: "I don't believe it is conscious of anything -- certainly not the necessity of husbanding its resources. It works blindly -- unconsciously -- like a machine which is at every moment guided and kept in motion by some power and intelligence foreign to itself."
    Thanks Wright for review in North American Review of Bowen's book; Metaphysics: Wright inclines to Mill, Bowen to the Scots. Probability and epistemology, causation and causality.
    Theory of probabilities.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1853 January 30, 1854 November 26; 2 ALsS; Cary, George S.
    Abstracting Orson Pratt's arguments against materialism.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1861-1864; 4 ALsS; Chase, Reginald Heber, 1832-1885
    Country's going to L; why? "Look at the photographic group of Uncle Abe & his Cabinet 'in council' -- and that will tell you why. A gorilla in the executive chair; Seward and Cameron looking like two pickpockets on trial..."
    Complains of the "bigoted malignity of the Lincoln despotism" and having been drafted. Does not wish to pay his way out or skedaddle: "My natural candor forbids me to give even the abolition tyranny such a very false impression of my motives & intentions." Will purchase a substitute.
    Supports Lincoln, "sincerely regretting certain of his peculiarities, & hoping that I may be spared to see the time when the interest of the nation will permit the election of a gentleman to the highest executive office." Sub rosa: has been considered to replace Taney on the court.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1853 February 1; ALS, calling card; Cheever, David W.
    Tutor Chase.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1868 October 26; ALS; Comfort, George F.
    Re: formation of an American Philological Society and reaction of American linguists.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1868 October 25; ALS; Curtis, George William, 1824-1892
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1864 October 31; ALS; Dodge, Lydia C.
    Inquiring into Wright's terms for delivering lecture to a natural history society in Hingham.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1852 August 10; ALS; Eden, John
    Inquiring how the knee gets on.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1875 July 6; ALS; Eliot, Charles William
    Cancelling Physics 1 due to low enrollment.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1850-1858; 6 ALsS; Fisher, George H.
    Letter of Oct. 1850 includes rough sketch of "Wright wasting the midnight oil," studying.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1868 November 4; 1874 October 28; 2 ALsS; Garrison, Wendell Phillips
    Re: reviews for The Nation.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1874 May 31; ALS; Godkin, Edwin Lawrence
    Defends his stance on women's suffrage, the natural difference between the sexes (and against John Stuart Mill).
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1866 February 25-March 14; 4 ALsS; Gould, Benjamin Apthorp, 1824-1896
    Re; controversy over lack of consultation on a paper, Dudley Observatory matter.
    Includes one letter from Wright to Gould (1866 March 2).
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, n.d.; ANS; Gray, Asa, 1810-1888
    Requesting return of a book.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1873 December 13; ALS; Grinnell, Charles E.
    Meeting of the sub-sub-committee on psychology.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1857 August 1, 5; 2 ALsS; Gurney, Ephraim Whitman
    Thoughts on his beach holiday.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1857 September 24, November 13; 2 ALsS
    Requesting a review of Blodgett's climatology.
  - Circular letters, 1855-1857; 5 Pr. Ls; Harvard Club
    Proposal to form a club of Harvard graduates; three notices of meetings; and notice that the club has decided to shutter and sell its rooms on Tremont for lack of support.
  - Invitations to Chauncey Wright, 1857 July 1; 1866 June 22; 2 Pr. Ls; Harvard College
    Invitation to dine with the class of 1852 (1857); ticket of admission to Class of 1857 exercises in the church, and invitation to class dar, 1866.
  - Letter of appointment to Chauncey Wright, 1870 March 15; LS; Harvard College
    Signed by Charles W. Eliot, appointing Wright as Lecturer on Psychology.
  - Petition to Chauncey Wright, 1874 October 27; DS; Harvard College. Students
    Petition to teach a course on the elements of mechanics.
  - letter to George Andrew, 1861 October 11; ALS; Hopkins, Erastus
    Letter of introduction for George F. Wright and family.
  - Invitations to Chauncey Wright, n.d.; 5 ALsS
    Miscellaneous invitations to dine, etc.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1864-1869; 7 ALsS; Ireland, Catherine Innes
    Thanks for the enjoyable article. Sympathizes in his whooping cough. Thoughts on Mill and his perspective on women: "I may deny his logical conclusions, from my very weakness you know; and why should I make myself a logician in order to convince myself of what I do not care to believe? But I am not sure that I dissent from Mr. Mill's conclusions yet, except the suffrage, and I may have to unmake my mind on that point" (1869 July 28).
    Includes one letters signed C. E. Ireland.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1873 December 31; n.d.; 2 ALsS; Johnson, William Woolsey
    Seeking a position in mathematics. Seeks to discover meaning of "mean distance."
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1861 January 23; 1863 May 6; 2 ALsS; Lesley, [unidentified]
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1860 October 1; ALS; Lesley, J. P., (J. Peter), 1819-1903
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1861 January 9; n.d.; 2 ALsS; Lesley, Joseph
    Letter of introduction for poor young man (not named).
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1864 September 25; 1868 February 9; 2 ALsS; Lesley, Mary
    Includes carte de visite of Mary Lesley by Whipple, ca.1862.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1862-1872; 14 ALsS; Lesley, Susan I., (Susan Inches), 1823-1904
    Travel in France.
    Readings; Ruskin.
    Mary Walker's death; Peter overflows with students at the Scientific Institute.
    Recovering from four days of extreme pain. She and Mr. Lesley are "just as sick as dogs of Spiritual Manifestations."
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1856 December 20; ALS; Logan, W. E.
    Seeking to establish telegraph connection between Montreal and Boston.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1856 January 25; ALS; Lyman, James F.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright (acknowledgment of gift), 1872 April 12; Pr. LS; Massachusetts Historical Society
    Acknowledging gift of Wright's Darwinism: Being an Examination of Mr. St. George Mivart's Genesis of Species.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1852 July 27; 1866 June 28; ALsS; Nautical Almanac
    Appointment as a "computer in the preparation of the Natuical Almanac"; arranging to prepare the Ephemeris of the moon.
    Letter from J. H. C. Coffin.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1872-1882; 4 ALsS; Norton, Charles Eliot, 1827-1908
    Glad Wright was able to dine with Darwin: "He is a man whose personal qualities, only to be known by acquaintance with him in his own home, complete and satisfy the highest conception of him that one may have formed from his books. He is one of the most satisfactory of men" (1872 September 5).
    Divide between his inner and outer man is greater than ever before. Has seen only one interesting person lately, Carlyle. Understands Darwin is not well, having worked too hard on his new book and too much with the microscope (1972 October 23).
    Obliged for the letters from Darwin, which he will make available to (1882 September 8).
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1855 October 12; 1859 May 1; n.d.; 3 ALsS; Oliver, James Edward, 1829-1895
    Re: Wright's Individuality theory.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, n.d.; ALS; Oliver, U. K.
    Re.: measuring height of the piazza by length of shadow.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1874 February 28; Postcard; Palfrey, John C.
  - Letter from Grandmother, 1906 May 22, 25; 2 ALsS; Pearson, Chauncey Wright
    His birthday.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1865 September 2; ALS; Peirce, Charles S., (Charles Sanders), 1839-1914
    Mill's discussion of free will is highly ingenious... "The contradictions in Hamilton are well brought out; but with a malicious intent. Mill wants to root out this philosophy, by adequate arguments or by inadequate ones..." Mathematics of a card trick.
  - Photograph, n.d.; Cabinet card
    Cabinet card, damaged, by Hardie and Schadee.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1860 August 6; n.d.; 2 ALsS; Rigston, John
    Letter of introduction for John C. Rivers, with p.s. by Rives.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1862 August 9; n.d.; 2 ALsS; Runkle, John Daniel
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1872 October 6; ALS; Sedgwick, Sara
    Visit of Mrs. William James and Mrs. Anderson, the latter a "champion of her sex & so hot & comic in the exposition of her views, that the weary & time worn topic of women's rights and women's wrongs was often brought up for discussion. She made me thing that after all Colleges might be good places for some women by & by for she was quite too indifferent to our tyrant's cow to spend her time in [illeg.], and she had a large intelligence that was worthy of the best cultivation."
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1858 August 25; ALS; Sheldon, D. S.
    Letter of introduction for Clemens Hirschl.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1854-1860; 4 ALsS; Sprague, Joseph W.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1865 November 24; ALS; Storer, Horatio R.
    Regarding articles on medical topics published by the Academy, including one of surgical removal of the uterus.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1850 February 13; 1850 August 14; 1871 April 8; n.d.; 3 ALsS; Thayer, James Bradley
    Fanny Kemble playing Shakespeare.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1851-1858; 6 ALsS; Theyer, William Sydney
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, n.d. (February 17); ALS; Underwood, Francis Henry
    Apologies for late payment.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1855 December 10; ALS; Van Vleck, J. M.
    Promises to repay his debt. Wishes he could still be studying mathematics with Wright, Runkle, and Oliver.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1862 August 6; ALS; Ware, D. E.
    Meditating a short vacation inland.
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1864 June 15; n.d.; 2 ALsS; Ware, William R. (William Robert)
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1852-1853; 4 ALsS; Wilder, D. P.
    Regarding a problem in Davis' plane trigonometry.
    Situated as he was last year, teaching the same branches, but without the higher classes (1852 September 27).
    Misunderstandings in Baltimore over Thanksgiving, "that day so fatal in New England to turkeys, chickens, mince-pies, plum-puddings, et cetera" (1852 November 29).
    Seeking solution to mathematical problem from Davies (1853 February 27).
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, 1852 November 19; ALS; Wright, Asher
  - Was the Act of Brutus in Killing Caesar Justifiable?, n.d.; AMs; Wright, Chauncey
    School essay(?)
  - Whether the Government of this Country Ought to Interfere in the Politics of Europe, to Aid or Countenance those Who are Struggling There for Liberty?, n.d.; AMs; Wright, Chauncey
  - Positivist Hymn (after Watts), n.d.; AMs; Wright, Chauncey
  - letter to Chauncey Wright, n.d. (August 24); ALS; T., J. B.
    Urging a visit to Northampton.